<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The end of Christ's advent a sermon preached in the cathedral-church of Norwich on the two and twentieth of June, 1684 / by Erasmus Warren, rector of Worlington in Suffolk.</title>
            <author>Warren, Erasmus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W965A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13523391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13523391</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67685)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1559:12, 2161:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The end of Christ's advent a sermon preached in the cathedral-church of Norwich on the two and twentieth of June, 1684 / by Erasmus Warren, rector of Worlington in Suffolk.</title>
                  <author>Warren, Erasmus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.H. jun. for Robert Clavell ... and sold by George Rose ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: facing t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at 1559:12 identified as Wing W965</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Person and offices --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, I, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:99937:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Errata</hi> diſturbing the ſens.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ADvertiſement,</hi> page 2. l. 6. r. 17, l. 11. r. 2 <hi>Tim,</hi> p. 2. l. 36. r. <hi>Which words contain theſe three Parts,</hi> p. 3. l. 11. r. <hi>Cleanneſs,</hi> l. 17 r. <hi>Aſſeveration,</hi> l. 19. r. <hi>Relativ,</hi> p 5. l. 1. r. <hi>come,</hi> l. 29. r. <hi>prudent,</hi> l. 37. r <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 6. l. 8. r. <hi>Pythagorean,</hi> l. 12. r. <hi>Colis,</hi> p. 7. l. 2. r. <hi>in,</hi> l. 9. r. <hi>Adoption,</hi> p. 8. l. 20 r. <hi>from,</hi> l. 38. r. <hi>more,</hi> p. 9. l. 11. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 14. l. 17. r. <hi>as,</hi> p. 15. l. 8. r. <hi>put,</hi> p. 16. l. 3. r. <hi>Intimation,</hi> p. 18. l. 6. r. <hi>means ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> p. 19. l. 7. r. <hi>ſcene,</hi> l. 34. r. <hi>unto,</hi> p. 27. l. 24. r. <hi>ſuſpicions.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The End of CHRIST'S Advent; A SERMON Preached in the CATHEDRAL-CHURCH OF NORWICH, ON THE Two and Twentieth of <hi>June,</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ERASM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S WARREN</hi> Rector of <hi>Worlington</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>H. H.</hi> Jun. for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and Sold by <hi>George Roſe</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99937:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99937:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in GOD ANTHONY Lord Biſhop OF NORWICH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHAT a worthy Pattern of Orthodox ſteddineſs your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> has been, in our infamous times of mobility and mutation, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all: And therefore this diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:99937:3"/> knew not whither ſo naturally to direct its motion, as to ſuch a Center. Nor was it ſooner determined into that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, but it was greatly confirmed and quickened in the ſame, by this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: That your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> was ever a ſtrenuous Aſſertor of Really Ancient and Catholick Truth. Yea, when others durſt not give it ſo much as due coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> afforded it generous Entertainment, and Honoured it with Zelous Vindication and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. And where Truth in general found ſuch noble Wellcome and Protection; the ſacred Verities here contained, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd themſelves intitled to kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, ſutable to their reſpective weight and dignity. This encouraged them to preſent themſelves to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> hands, when the joynt importunity of Friends and Strangers, temted them from mine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99937:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I could wiſh, <hi>my Lord,</hi> that the Sermon held better proportion to its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſubject. But ſo pregnant and vaſtly fruitful is that; that to diſcourſe it up to its <hi>genuine faecundity,</hi> would be a task too great for the Tongues of <hi>Angels;</hi> and therefore no wonder if mine faultered in it.</p>
            <p>It was grave advice of the wiſe<note n="*" place="margin">Porph. in vit.</note> 
               <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Not to carry the Pictures of the Gods in little Rings.</hi> Thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating how improper it is, to exhibit the DEITY in narrow Symbols, and pourtray His MAJESTY in ſlighty ſemblances; to ſtamp His Greatneſs in a trifling impreſs, and crowd him into a diminutive and incompetent Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. This admirable Rule I muſt own I have violated, nor need any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach me as guilty in the caſe, but my conſcious apprehenſions. I know I have
<pb facs="tcp:99937:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> injured the Divineſt JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to magnifie Him. But ſo muſt the beſt do as well as I, that dare venture to deſcribe Him in His loweſt Glories: Tho this is extremely laudative too; as it beſpeaks Him exalted above all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation.</p>
            <p>Should any go about to Paint a Voice, to ſhow its ſweetneſs; or to Landskip Muſic, to expreſs its harmony: Their endeavours muſt needs prove inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, becauſe Art affords no Analogous Images or Types ſo curious as can exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie them. And for the ſame reaſon, vane muſt the attemts of all Mortals be, that would fully accompt for JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S'S <hi>Perfections.</hi> They want expreſſions to decipher them, nor can they tell where to find a ſupply. Were Rhetorick it ſelf Subpoena'd in, with all the copious variety it has; and ſet to declare His inexplicable nature, or
<pb facs="tcp:99937:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>indearing</hi> favours to the Children of Men; all it could ſay, would amount but to florid and decent obloquy; to an elegant Libell, or Gentiel diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But then (which is the ſcope of all this) <hi>how happy, my Lord, are we Chriſtians, that ſerve a Maſter, of ſuch ineffable magnificence.</hi> A Prince ſo incomparably Sweet and Heavenly, that there is no uttering His nature or his kindneſs. To at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temt to do it, is at once to undertake an impoſſible work, and run our ſelves directly upon moſt certain fruſtration.</p>
            <p>Pray, <hi>my Lord,</hi> I moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, to this <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S (the Glorious, but wronged Argument of my Diſcourſe) that I may ſerve Him conſcionably in my inferior capacity; and honour Him in imitating that <hi>rare example</hi> of vigilance and fidelity;
<pb facs="tcp:99937:5"/> which your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> in your eminent and deſerved ſtation, laudably ſets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me. So I ſhall be ſure to approve my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips ever obedient Son and Servant,</hi> Eraſmus Warren.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99937:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Tim. 1.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S came into the World to ſave Sinners.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O excite and call forth our beſt attention to the Words rehearſed, the HOLY GHOST has prefac'd them in a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn manner, and grac'd them with an high and pompous Introduction. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation.</hi> What more could have been ſaid in ſo ſhort a Period, to rowze us to ſerious animadverſion of them?</p>
            <p>There are <hi>two</hi> things that mightily commend a Doctrine or Aphoriſm, to the fixed notice and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Men. The <hi>Verity,</hi> and <hi>Acceptability</hi> thereof. And both theſe are eminently combined in the recited ſentence: For it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> or credible <hi>ſaying,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>of all</hi> reception or <hi>acceptation.</hi> If I can prove the firſt, the latter will follow of its own accord. If I can make it out to be <hi>True,</hi> that CHRIST came into the World to ſave ſinners; the Poſition muſt needs be very <hi>Acceptable,</hi> becauſe of ſingular advantage to us.</p>
            <p>And that it is a great and notorious Truth, may be argued with powerful and evictive evidence, from theſe three Topicks.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99937:6"/>
               <item>1. Divine Teſtimony.</item>
               <item>2. The Titles of CHRIST. And</item>
               <item>3. The courſe or tenour of his Terreſtrial Life.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, This is manifeſt from <hi>inſpired Teſtimonies;</hi> which are every where reſperſed in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo I paſs by all thoſe Types and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, of his coming as a SAVIOUR, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Old: Which might well be call'd in as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exceptionable witneſſes to the Propoſition. It may ſerve our purpoſe to note, that the Four Evangeliſts confirm the Article, by their joint ſuffrage and atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.11.</note> St. <hi>Matthew</hi> aſſerts it in his Goſpel; <hi>The Son of Man is come to ſave that which is loſt.</hi> St. <hi>Mark</hi> avers it in his;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>I came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to Repentance.</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> in his; <hi>The Son of Man is not come to deſtroy Mens lives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.56.</note> 
               <hi>but to ſave them.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> in his;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 12.47.</note> 
               <hi>I came not to judge the World, but to ſave the World.</hi> And to theſe in this caſe, are Apoſtles Symphonous and the exactly conſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. But we need not the concurrence of Parallel Quotations out of their Writings, to ſettle us in the belief of ſo generally a received and approved Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is apparent from <hi>the Various denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that are given to CHRIST,</hi> he is ſtiled a <hi>King.</hi> And it is the Office of a King to ſave his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from the miſchiefs and hoſtilities that their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies machinate and contrive againſt them. He is called a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> the <hi>Good Shepherd;</hi> and it is the part of a Good Shepherd, to ſave his Flock from ſpoil and violence; and ſuch piteous havock and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laniations, as ravenous Wolves and rapacious Vermin would make amongſt them. He is ſaid to be the LIFE: And therefore when he came, it was (moſt aſſuredly) to ſave us from Death; Or (as himſelf
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99937:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> expreſſes it) <hi>That we might have life, and that we might have it more abundantly.</hi> But what need we go farther than the venerable Appellative, mention'd in the Text, JESUS? In this we may read him the Author of our Salvation, in great Letters. To that ſenſe was the name expounded, when by the Angel it was firſt impoſed: <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>for he ſhall SAVE his People from their ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is Evident from <hi>the manner or condition of his Life,</hi> in the ſtate of humiliation, and the days of his fleſh. It was little elſe than a concatenation or producted ſeries of miſeries and ſufferings; all which muſt have a direct tendency and ſubſervience to the Salvation of ſinners. For if this were not the drift of his Travels and Penances, it will be hard to find the reaſon of their Infliction; the nature of God being infinitely good, and the Providence of Heaven accurately juſt, and the perſon of our LORD, not only immaculate, but of perfect Sanctity. For tho he was called a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and counted a <hi>Daemoniac,</hi> and reckoned with Tranſgreſſors; yet he knew no ſin, nor was there any guile found in his mouth. No, he was harmleſs, and blameleſs, and the SON of GOD without rebuke: Whiter than the Snow, and Purer than the Light, and Brighter if poſſible, than Holineſs it ſelf. None could charge him with the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of a Treſpaſs againſt GOD; nor in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Proceſs convict him of a crime, or any thing like it, againſt Men. He was the moſt glorious Practiſt of all Righteouſneſs that ever lived: And as he came to fulfill his Fathers will, ſo he did it in exacteſt meaſures. His life was clear from all miſcarriages, and his obedience commenſurate to the whole Law, in its fulleſt Latitude of injunctions. He was ſo far from reſiſting the Heavenly mind, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99937:7"/> acting contrary to the Divine pleaſure; that he never violated any <hi>Political</hi> or <hi>Humane</hi> Sanctions, provided they were juſt in their Conſtitution, and in their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance warrantable.</p>
            <p>And hence it follows, that when he was afflicted and ſtrangely abuſed, it was not for any <hi>perſonal</hi> faults or delinquencies, becauſe he <hi>had</hi> none. And ſince he could not ſuffer and die as he did, for any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquities or miſdemeanors of his <hi>own,</hi> it remains he did ſo for <hi>nobler</hi> cauſes, and to higher and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ends and purpoſes. To perform a work of ampleſt Charity, and an office of Mercy for the World of ſinners. To reconcile them to the DEITY they had Rebelliouſly ſlighted, and prevent the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of thoſe precious Souls they had raſhly forfeited; by giving his Blood for the deletery of their Offences, and his ineſtimable life for the price of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>And to make it clear that the <hi>paſſive part</hi> of his life upon Earth, miniſtred to the deſign of expiating our ſins, and redeeming us from the puniſhments and torturous ſeverities due unto them; he is ſaid in Scripture, to <hi>bear our ſins;</hi> to be <hi>wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions;</hi> to be <hi>bruiſed for our iniquities:</hi> and where there is mention made of his diſmal Sufferings, they are referred to <hi>us,</hi> and put as it were upon <hi>our</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt. And truly unleſs by his Sufferings he ſaves us from ſin; he is <hi>falſly</hi> ſtiled a SAVIOUR and DELIVERER by the Infallible Writers. For as every one ſees, they that are CHRIST'S, are liable to infelicities, as well as others. To as many fears, and dangers, and miſeries, and deaths as any in the World. Yea, for their being the Servants and Diſciples of JESUS, they are <hi>more</hi> liable to theſe, than <hi>other Men.</hi> So that, if his ſufferings do not reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99937:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> them from their ſins, he is in <hi>no ſenſe</hi> a SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOUR at all, but rather a <hi>betrayer</hi> of his people: By ingaging them in that Religion, which expoſeth them to thoſe evils, that otherwiſe would fall more ſeldom, and leſs heavy upon them.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine then is True, <hi>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S came into the World to ſave ſinners.</hi> But <hi>Why he rather than another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is eaſie, and ſoon given; <hi>becauſe none beſides him was able to do it.</hi> To vanquiſh death, and deprive it of its ſting; to conquer Hell, and diſarm it of its power; to ſatisfie the Law, and to bear away its curſe; to pacifie the wrath of an incenſed GOD, by doing right to his offended Juſtice; and to redeem a number of captivated Spirits, by expiating the guilt of their horrid impieties; is a work of no leſs than inſuperable difficulty, to any but him with whom all things are poſſible. If the weight and preſſure of this ponderous burthen, had been laid upon the ſhoulders of the ſtrongeſt Angel, it would have ſunk him immediately into perdition, and there have kept him for ever and ever. And if the loftieſt <hi>Angel</hi> could not ſave the World, how much leſs able is any <hi>Man</hi> to do it? The Soul plung'd into Hell Five Thouſand Years ago, is as far from ſatisfying for her <hi>own</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probities, by what ſhe hath indured; as if ſhe were thrown in but <hi>yeſterday.</hi> And when ſhe has there been excruciated Five Thouſand times as long, her ſatisfactions will ſtill be as ſhort and imperfect, as they were the firſt moment ſhe began to flame. And if a man by ſuffering the infernal plagues, cannot make amends for his <hi>own</hi> enormities; then how much leſs for the ſuperabounding wickedneſs of <hi>all the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99937:8"/>
            <p>That no Creatures are able to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> for our ſins, and ſo to <hi>ſave</hi> our Souls; is demonſtrated thus.</p>
            <p>This Satisfaction they muſt effect, either by <hi>duties</hi> or <hi>ſufferings:</hi> But by neither of theſe ways can they do it; and therefore not at all.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. Not by <hi>Duties.</hi> For the beſt obedience perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by them is due to GOD as the Author of their beings. And if all their obedience muſt go to HIM, as payment of a debt which they owe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; how can any of it be imploy'd towards Satisfaction for others? Yea God is not only the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their beings, but moreover the Donor of that very power, whereby they yield obedience to himſelf. And ſo they are the more oblig'd to Him ſtill, but have the leſs ability to ſatisfie either for their own, or others immoralities. Nor</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Can they do it in way of <hi>puniſhment.</hi> For our ſins being perpetrated againſt an Infinite Majeſty, do ſo become of an Infinite malignity, and are not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated but by an Infinite penalty. But creatures, being finite, are utterly incapable of puniſhments that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, unleſs they be ſo in way of duration. And ſhould any undertake to ſuffer puniſhments <hi>always</hi> to endure, thereby to ſatisfie for the ſins of Men; when would this ſatisfaction (ſo making) be finiſht? How would our Salvation ever be accompliſht? And becauſe none could do this mighty Work, beſides that adorable one in the Text, therefore he was pleaſed to ſet his hand to it; <hi>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S came into the World to ſave ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>by what means is it done?</hi> Why, by <hi>entire ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he made for our treſpaſſes.</hi> Which ſatisfaction lyes <hi>chiefly,</hi> if not <hi>only,</hi> in his ruful <hi>ſufferings.</hi> For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made under the Law, by virtue of his condition,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99937:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> he was ſtrictly oblig'd, to yield an Adequate obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereunto, on his own accompt. Nor does his active Obedience ſeem to be an ingredient into his ſatisfaction, but only as it may be reckoned a piece of his paſſion; in his free and voluntary ſubmiſſion <hi>to,</hi> and meek and lowly ſuſception <hi>of,</hi> the Obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial ſtate. And therefore I ſay, His ſufferings are the <hi>Matter</hi> of his ſatisfaction. And theſe are either <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal,</hi> in regard of which, he is ſaid to <hi>bear our ſins in his body:</hi> Or elſe <hi>Spiritual;</hi> in reference to which, <hi>his Soul</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>made an offering for ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Efficacy</hi> of his Satisfaction reſults from his tranſcendent merit. That merit from the ſuperlative dignity of his Perſon, That dignity from the peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs excellence of his Nature; that is, his Divinity. Which in his miraculous conception, was complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or connected to our deſpicable Fleſh, and ſtooped to an intimate conjunction with humanity. And tho the way of its union and humble copulation, was ever ſo myſterious, as to be unintelligible; yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof and condemnation of daring Haereſiarchs, it is fairly elucidated by the Council of <hi>Calcedon.</hi> For there the Fathers (adhering to Decrees of Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Synods) Orthodoxly defined; that CHRIST is perfect GOD, and real Man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>unconfuſedly, unchangedly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividedly, inſeparately:</hi> Thereby rightly defending the unity of his <hi>Perſon:</hi> Truly maintaining the <hi>duplicity</hi> of his <hi>Nature:</hi> and plainly aſſerting, and piouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating, the reſpective <hi>proprieties</hi> of <hi>each Nature</hi> to be ſtill retained, in their genuine diſtinctneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. But not to digreſs</p>
            <p>This Satisfaction <hi>Socinus</hi> denies, affirming poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <hi>Divinae Juſtitiae neque ſatisfeciſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſp. par. <hi>1.</hi> cap.</note> 
               <hi>neque ut ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieret, opus fuiſſe.</hi> That CHRIST <hi>neither hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99937:9"/> ſatisfied the Divine Juſtice, nor was it neceſſary, that it ſhould be ſatisfied.</hi> Yea, which is worſe, he ranks this Doctrine amongſt <hi>planè nugatoria, meer trifles.</hi> And which is groſſeſt of all, he calls the opinion, <hi>Frigidum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat. cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>falſum, abſurdum, faedè ſumméque injuſtum, &amp; horribiliter blaſphemum: Cold, falſe, abſurd, vilely and extremely injuſt, and horribly blaſphemous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in confutation of this black, and wild, and pernicious figment; we are taught from above, that CHRIST died <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>For us.</hi> And that not only as an <hi>Example,</hi> but as a REDEEMER. And therefore he is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a price,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ranſom.</hi> And we are farther inſtructed that he died <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for our ſins:</hi> and was <hi>delivered</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for our offences:</hi> and ſuffered <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for our iniquities.</hi> All which phraſes (to them that underſtand the Greek Idiom, and the ſenſe of the expreſſions, as commonly uſed by Maſters of that language, and Writers in it) do clearly ſignifie; that our ſins are not only the <hi>final,</hi> but <hi>impulſive</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious</hi> cauſe of CHRIST'S death.</p>
            <p>And therefore we are told farther ſtill; that he was a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> for us. Not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an offering;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a propitiation:</hi> Yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a curſe.</hi> Which implies again, and irrefragably proves, that he did not only die, <hi>noſtro bono, for our Good;</hi> but <hi>noſtro loco,</hi> in our ſtead. And that his death was really ſatisfactory in that ſenſe, which our Church em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically teaches in her common Office, <hi>He ſuffered death upon the Croſs, for our Redemption, and made there a full, perfect, and ſufficient ſacrifice, oblation, and ſatisfaction, for the ſins of the whole World.</hi> And by means of this ſatisfaction, the diſpleaſure of ALMIGHTY GOD, who was provoked, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed. The Equity of his inexorable Juſtice, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99937:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> was injured; is vindicated. The Authority of his indiſpenſable Law, which was prevaricated; is fenced and ſecured. The guilt of the Criminous, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were corrupted; is exterminated, and aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And the guilty, moſt guilty ſinners, which muſt have been condemned; may now be certainly and eternally ſaved.</p>
            <p>But there is one Query ſtill behind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what conditions may we through</hi> CHRIST <hi>obtain Salvation?</hi> They are theſe two; <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> And therefore it is ſaid, <hi>He that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall be ſaved:</hi> and, <hi>The Righteous ſhall go into life Eternal.</hi> But if in this faith there happens a failure, or an interciſion ſalls out in our Righteouſneſs; then <hi>Repentance</hi> comes in as an uſeful Supplement, and where it is unfeigned, makes amends for all defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencies.</p>
            <p>Upon this Queſtion <hi>another</hi> may be grafted; Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Whether we are to be ſaved by CHRIST'S im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs?</hi> The judgments of moſt have leaned to the affirmative. And tho I muſt not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to determine the Problem; yet I may venture to aſſert of this prevailing opinion, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its great reputation and Authority, it is liable at leaſt to <hi>one notable exception;</hi> and meet to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with <hi>one prudent caution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Exception</hi> is this: <hi>It is not ſo perſpicuouſly laid down in Scripture, as the Patrons and Propugners of it do pretend.</hi> It is ſaid indeed in the 4th of <hi>Rom. That</hi> Abraham <hi>believed GOD, and it was IMP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TED to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> But the ſenſe of that Text, can only be this. GOD gave <hi>Abraham</hi> a Promiſe; and <hi>Abraham</hi> gave credit to the Promiſe he made; as it was fit he ſhould upon the accompt of his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity. And <hi>in</hi> ſo doing, he did a righteous act; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99937:10"/> 
               <hi>for</hi> ſo doing GOD reckoned him, in <hi>that inſtance,</hi> a righteous perſon. But what's this to the imputing of CHRIST'S righteouſneſs?</p>
            <p>In the ſame Chapter it is remembred, that <hi>David</hi> deſcribeth the Bleſſedneſs of that man, unto whom GOD <hi>imputeth righteouſneſs.</hi> And his words are theſe: <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered. Bleſſed is the man unto whom the LORD will not impute ſin.</hi> So that all the <hi>imputing of Righteouſneſs</hi> here, amounts to no more, than a <hi>non-imputation</hi> of ſin. And therefore this place does planely ſubvert, rather than ſupport the controverted Article.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. That <hi>CHRIST is made unto us Righteouſneſs.</hi> But how ſhould this be done, ſay the favourers of the opinion, unleſs by <hi>imputation?</hi> Yet the whole verſe runs thus: <hi>But of him are ye in CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S who of GOD is made unto us Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and Redemption.</hi> Now durſt any maintain, that CHRIST is our Redemption, by <hi>imputing</hi> it to us only? Yet as well they may hold <hi>that,</hi> as infer from the words, that he is our <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> by <hi>imputation.</hi> For the one is there ſaid to be <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted,</hi> as much as the <hi>other.</hi> And therefore for ought that is colligible thence, he muſt be the one, in the ſame way and notion, that he is the other. And is he not both, becauſe he procured both? And for the ſame reaſon he is ſaid to be <hi>our peace</hi> too; becauſe he purchas'd and procur'd it for us.</p>
            <p>Again, they allege that of St. <hi>Paul. By the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of one</hi> (that is, CHRIST) <hi>many ſhall be made Righteous.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19.</note> But can any be made <hi>righteous</hi> by <hi>his obedience,</hi> except it be <hi>imputed?</hi> I anſwer; It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable they may: And theſe very words ſeem to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99937:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> to another ſenſe. The ſame Pen which wrote <hi>them,</hi> has recorded <hi>this</hi> of CHRIST likewiſe: That <hi>He humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the CROSS:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wherefore,</hi> (for which very condeſcenſive obedience of his) <hi>GOD has highly exalted Him, and given him a Name above every Name.</hi> Or (as we read elſewhere) has given Him <hi>all power in Heaven and Earth.</hi> And ſo power to diſpenſe Righteouſneſs unto his People. And ſo the obedience of CHRIST, may become inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to the making many Righteous, tho it be not imputed to them, becauſe it was a means to intitle him <hi>to,</hi> and inveſt him <hi>in,</hi> a power of <hi>diſpenſing</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to men.</p>
            <p>Theſe are chief Texts upon which the Doctrine of Imputation has been founded. And from theſe it has been as boldly and magiſterially taught and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, as if it were there delivered <hi>totidem verbis,</hi> in expreſs words. But whether they teach it ſo clearly, and juſtifie it ſo fully, and make it ſo very neceſſary to be believed as ſome imagine; let the intelligent judg. I ſpeak nothing in a definitive or dogmatical way. Only I find that our Church in her Articles, ſays not thus; but that <hi>we are accompted righteous, only for the merit of our LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thoſe of us that have cordially embraced this opinion, and think we have reaſon to adhere to the ſame; let us always do it with <hi>this caution: <hi>Never ſo re'ly upon the righteouſneſs of CHRIST, as to neglect righteouſneſs in our ſelves.</hi>
               </hi> For that's the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence (it is to be feared) which this perſwaſion has upon many: While they truſt to be juſtified by their SAVIOUR'S righteouſneſs, they diſregard righteouſneſs in <hi>themſelves:</hi> Without which, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of CHRIST ſhall never be imputed, tho
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99937:11"/> the Doctrine in diſpute were true. And to take us off the neglect of Righteouſneſs in our ſelves, we may conſider; there is nothing more earneſtly or frequently urged in the ſacred Volume, than our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>actually</hi> righteous. <hi>Awake to Righteouſneſs: fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after Righteouſneſs: live unto Righteouſneſs: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on the breſt-plate of Righteouſneſs: being filled with the fruits of Righteouſneſs.</hi> And not to multiply Quotations, St. <hi>John,</hi> let us hear ſpeak once for all, <hi>He that doth righteouſneſs is righteous.</hi> So that he alone can be the <hi>truly</hi> righteous man, that is <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> ſo.</p>
            <p>And beſides; we are required to be <hi>Holy as GOD is Holy.</hi> But GOD we know is not <hi>imputatively</hi> Holy, and therefore neither muſt <hi>we</hi> be ſo only. But as his holineſs is intrinſic, natural, and eſſential: ſo ours muſt be inherent, proper, and perſonal. Elſe it can never ſymbolize with <hi>his,</hi> nor come up to a juſt reſemblance of it; as it ought to do, in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to that Apoſtolical Precept; <hi>Put on the new man, which after GOD, is created in Righteouſneſs and true holineſs,</hi> Eph. 4.24.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, ſuch <hi>actual,</hi> ſolid, and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Righteouſneſs as this, is indiſpenſably needful to qualifie us for the happineſs of the future ſtate. For ſhould impious miſcreants that are deſtitute of it, be tranſlated thither; they would be but as Batts in the Sun-ſhine; and the felicities about them, would be matter of trouble and uneaſineſs to them, through want of righteouſneſs. For the bleſſedneſs of a ſtate reſults from the congruity betwixt the excellencies in it, and the perſons that poſſeſs it. Now unleſs we be righteous, there is no ſymmetry or agreement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our diſpoſitions, and the Heavenly Beatitudes: and therefore were we placed in Heaven its ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out righteouſneſs, we could not be happy.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99937:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And this (by the way) gives a plauſible accompt, and the true reaſon why God impoſes duties upon us. Not becauſe acting them is beneficial; or omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, any way detrimental to himſelf: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereby we might improve our righteouſneſs, and acquire ſuch habits of goodneſs to our ſelves, as might elevate our Souls into a meet capacity, of injoying the Glories of the Eternal World, and of being beatifi'd in that fruition.</p>
            <p>And for this reaſon CHRIST <hi>cannot</hi> ſave ſinners, but on terms of righteouſneſs. Not only becauſe it is otherwiſe decreed, but becauſe it is <hi>impoſſible;</hi> there being no ſalvation, no ſuch thing as happineſs to be had, without actual righteouſneſs, even in the preſence of GOD himſelf. An unrighteous Soul is as incapable of the Beatifie Viſion, as a blind Eye is of ſeeing the light of the Sun.</p>
            <p>And therefore as for <hi>Infants, Idiots,</hi> and the like, who cannot be indued with this <hi>ſort</hi> of righteouſneſs; mercy ſaves them upon another accompt, and their happineſs may be another thing: conſiſting not ſo much in accumulated pleaſures, as in an Anodynous condition, and a ſtate of Indolence. For the Higher life having ſeveral degrees of bliſs in it, the loweſt of theſe degrees (which falls to the lot of the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned parties) may lye chiefly in an exemption or total immunity from all kind of troubles. At leaſt the felicities cannot be ſo ſweet, and ſtrong, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate; as thoſe of more perfectly righteous Spirits.</p>
            <p>Having made good what the Text aſſerts, that <hi>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S came into the World to ſave Sinners:</hi> And reſolved three material Queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Salvation: The Firſt, touching the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; the Second, the Means; and the Third, the Terms and Conditions thereof: Now may ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99937:12"/> Inferences ſeaſonably come in, as are moſt deducible from the words.</p>
            <p>The Firſt, This;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If man had not ſinned, GOD had not been Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</hi> The very end of his Advent, or coming in a Body, was to ſave Sinners: If therefore there had been no ſinners to ſave, he had never ſo come into the World. Some have thought and taught other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: and amongſt the reſt, that noble and renowned <hi>Picus</hi> of <hi>Mirandula.</hi> Who undertook to maintain, that, <hi>Si</hi> Adam <hi>non peccaſſet, Deus fuiſſet incarnatus, ſed non crucifixus. If</hi> Adam <hi>had not ſinned, GOD had been incarnate, but not crucified:</hi> Which is highly improbable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What a bitter Lamentation may we juſtly take up for the unbelieving Jews?</hi> CHRIST is come to ſave them, and they ſtill expect him. He died <hi>for</hi> them, he died <hi>amongſt</hi> them; and yet they think he is not born. Being given up to a Reprobate mind, and ſtrong deluſions; and a ſpirit of dull and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous incredulity; they will not be perſwaded that he aſſumed our Nature, and <hi>tabernacled</hi> amongſt us, according to the expreſſion of the HOLY GHOST.</p>
            <p>He anſwered the Quality and character of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah in all points; ſave only that he was not a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Prince, as they miſconceiv'd he ſhould be. Which groſs and unhappy notion of theirs, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the foundation of all theirs prejudice, and malice againſt him. He was born when the Regal and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative power was departed from the Jews: His Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a Virgin; of the City of <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Judah;</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>David.</hi> All which was to be. And, which is more, when he Preached to the Jews, and converted with them, he atteſted his Divinity with ſigns and wonders, with Glorious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99937:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> prodigies and ſtupendious Miracles. Which all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prevailed ſo far, that they entred him in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Regiſter of their Prieſts, by this Title; <hi>IESVS the Son of the living GOD, and of the Virgin Mary.</hi> But when all was done, they rejected him at laſt; and count him no better to this very day, than a Grand Impoſtor, and baſe and curſed Seducer of their Nation.</p>
            <p>O let us pity them, and from our hearts bewail their deplorable condition. We can hardly beſtow our tears better, than upon that blind, and obſtinate, and forſaken People.</p>
            <p n="3">3. '<hi>How vaſt, abounding, and illimited, is</hi> CHRIST'S <hi>affection towards us?</hi> It is high as the Heavens, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable as Eternity, infinite as Himſelf.' It has far out-acted all Romance, and ſcorns to be contain'd within the compaſs of Hyperboles. In compare with this, the wildeſt extravagancies, and moſt impoſſible ſtories of licentious fiction, may ſeem both probable and modeſt things. That CHRIST JESUS ſhould come, and come into the World, to ſave ſinners; Lord what a Love was this, and who can Expreſs it! Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it? Alas in words there's too great penury to do it. Yea thoughts themſelves are much too narrow to conceive it. When they unite with ſtrongeſt force, and even dilate their whole capacity, and ſtrive to graſp it in their apprehenſion; they ſtrain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves quite beyond their power, and ſo diſſolve in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confus'd diſtraction, leaving the mind in ſweet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement.</p>
            <p>Miraculous love! ſuch as none but a GOD could ever have manifeſted. And ſo manifeſted, as no men upon Earth durſt ever have deſired. For us once to have whiſpered ſuch a thing in the ALMIGHTIES Ear, as his Sons Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99937:13"/> for our Redemption; tho with lips laid in the duſt, and ſpirits cloath'd with loweſt humility; would have been the higheſt pitch of Unpardonable Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a blaſphemy as loud as Thunder. But that monſtruous ſavour wich the boldeſt durſt not ask, GOD freely granted without requeſt: and ſo much the greater was his love for that.</p>
            <p>'The HOLY GHOST'S deſcription of this matchleſs love, is ſtrange and unuſual, to make it the more emphatical, Eph. 1.18. <hi>That ye may be able to comprehend the bredth, and length, and depth, and heighth of</hi> CHRIST'S <hi>love.</hi> We no where read of Love deſcribed thus. Yet this, I ſay, is ſo far from being improper and abſurd, that it is moſt apt and congruous.' For while he imputes Phyſical dimenſions to it, he does but illuſtrate and commend its excellence, making it even a firm and ſolid Body of Love; ſuch as for the unparallel'd perfection and peculiarity of it, is not to be found but in the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed DEITY, which is love eſſential. O conſider this love and wonder; conſider it, I ſay, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it. That GOD the FATHER ſhould ſend his SON; and GOD the SON ſhould come himſelf; and come to ſuch a place, and come in ſuch a way, and come to ſuch an end; what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of love was here? What mighty love? What marvellous Love? What boundleſs, peerleſs, paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Love? Speak O Heavens, and declare O Earth, if ever ye beheld the like. What ſhall I ſay to it? O what ſhall I ſay concerning it? My beſt way is to hold my peace. I will do therefore as I now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; think and wonder, but ſpeak no more; Aſtoniſht ſilence is the fitteſt Eloquence.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99937:13"/>
            <p>And truly we may well give over ſpeaking, and ſay no more of this wondrous Love. For I remember that famous Doctor S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who (as all muſt grant) wanted no Elocution; was remarkably plung'd in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing about it. He was egregiouſly learned and inſpired too; yet treating of this incomprehenſible love, he was preſently non-pluſt, and fain to deliver himſelf at a ſtrange rate, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. writing no leſs than contradiction. <hi>That ye may be able to know the Love of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>that paſſeth knowledge.</hi> What a ſignificant inconſiſtency? What a ſweet and pregnant incongruity is here? Can we meaſure that which is boundleſs? Can we fathom that which is bottomleſs? Can we know that love which paſſeth knowledge? But thus we muſt talk of this ſurpaſſing love, nor can we do it in better terms: To ſuch abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties it drives our ſhallowneſs, to diſcourſe of its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity.</p>
            <p>But then while they live, let none of CHRIST's ſincere and hearty Proſelytes, go about to queſtion the divine love to them. To do that <hi>now,</hi> will be too diſingenious and unreaſonable. For he that contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates this illuſtrious act, of his coming into this World to ſave it; and fluctuates and ſtaggers in the belief of JESUS his indulgence to his People: May next diſpute, whether the Sun ſhines at noon-day or no; and doubt if the plaineſt and moſt demonſtrable truths, be not fallacious and incertain things.</p>
            <p>Herein he has given us, a ſtronger argument, a ſurer token, a clearer evidence, a larger inſtance of his love, <hi>ſince</hi> mans defection and apoſtacy; than ever he did <hi>afore.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99937:14"/>
            <p>To go a little farther; Since the love and kindneſs of the SON of God, has been, and is ſo ardent to us; let this holy flame warm our Souls with reciprocal affections to him again. And let the egreſſions of our love to him, correſpond to his way of expreſſing love to us. That is, as he has manifeſted his love, in <hi>actual</hi> coming to us; ſo let us ſhew ours, in paſſionate <hi>deſires</hi> of going to him.</p>
            <p>Were we exalted to the higheſt Glories; were we ſurrounded with bliſs, and incircled with Joy, and crowned with Honour and Immortality: In a word were we above in the heavenly ſtate; yet were we there without CHRIST, who brought us thither; methinks we ſhould be impatient even of that ſweet condition, and find a wearineſs and reſtleſneſs in our ſelves, till we might paſs into his wiſhed preſence, where-ever it ſhould be. But how much greater cauſe have we now, of longing to be where our REDEEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER is; when we are not in Heaven, but on Earth; in a ſinning, ſuffering, dying ſtate; which were it not that it leads to a better, would not indeed be worth the having.</p>
            <p>Methinks O Chriſtians! As oft as our dear and lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing SAVIOUR comes into our minds (and ſure he can never be long out) our glowing hearts ſhould preſently take fire, and burn with pathetic longings after him; and we ſhould not care, either what we did, or what we ſuffered, ſo we might but aſcend unto his MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>Thus it was with that glorious Martyr <hi>S. Ignatius, S. Johns</hi> Diſciple, and Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Antioch.</hi> He profeſſes of himſelf in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans;</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Either of things viſible, or inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo I may injoy</hi> JESUS CHRIST. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99937:14"/> &amp;c. <hi>Let fire, and the Croſs, and troops of wild Beaſts; let cuttings, and lancings, and rackings of my bones; let tearing of my members, and the diſſolution of my Body, and the chaſtiſement of the Devil come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, ſo I may poſſeſs</hi> JESUS CHRIST. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>'Tis good for me to die for</hi> JESUS CHRIST; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>rather than to reign over the Ends of the Earth.</hi> And a little after he cries out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the</hi> LORD <hi>I deſire,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>him I ſeek.</hi> Thus the holy man breathed, and thus his holy Soul panted after JESUS. O that our deſires would riſe and run, and at ſuch rate, as they have greateſt reaſon to do continually.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>How ſtudious, officious, and laborious ſhould we be, for the good of Men; though in what we do we debaſe our ſelves, and ſtoop to the moſt inferior im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments?</hi> The SON of GOD came into the World. And to what end? To be ſole and abſolute Monarch of the Earth? And to act pompous ſtate, or ſplendid greatneſs, in, or over it? Did he come to wear a Robe, and to ſway a Sceptre? To live in Honour, and to rule in Glory? To have Princes for his ſervants, and Kings for his attendants, &amp; Puiſſant Emperours for his companions? Or did he come to erect his Pavilion in the Clouds, and to make the Skies his ſpatious territories? Did he come to be crowned with the Stars, and to be clothed with the Sun? To have Cherubim for his Guard, and Seraphim for his train? To threaten with accents as piercing as lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to command with a voice as dreadful as Thunder; and to receive the homage and proſtrate adorations of all the Inhabitants of the Univerſe?</p>
            <p>This I confeſs, and a great deal more, would have been but highly befitting his MAJESTY. But wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99937:15"/> different from all this, was the end of JESUS his coming in the Fleſh. It was to ſave Sinners: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable duſt and ſorry worms. Then which he could have made a thouſand times more, and a thouſand times better creatures with a word. And this was a mean work for him, eſpecially conſidering how it was to be done. For he was to ſave them, by ſatisfying for them: And to ſatisfie, by Suffering. By Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhame, by Suffering pain, by Suffering death, and all that innocence could indure.</p>
            <p>BUT leſs then we cannot learn from hence, than to ſerve Mankind with a pious induſtry; and never to ſtick at our own diminution, ſo we may contribute to their Salvation. An example of this, is the great S. <hi>Paul:</hi> I will very gladly ſpend, and be ſpent for you. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. '<hi>How confident may we be of our Souls Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity?</hi> For were not their Exiſtence laſting, and their Life extended beyond the term of this tranſitory ſtate; our bleſſed LORD need not have come to purchaſe their Salvation, But ſince he was born to ranſom them from Hell, and to put them in a capacity of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſs; this fully evinceth, that they ſhall have being, when this World has none, and live through the longeſt tracts of Eternity.' This Heathens ſaw by their glimmering light. For as the Ingenious Poet ſang, <hi>Morte carent animae.</hi>— And another, <hi>Sunt aliquid manes, lethum non omnia fiunt.</hi> Ghoſts are ſomewhat upon which the fangs of Death don't faſten.</p>
            <p>Our Spirits are not of ſo mean a make, as at Death to periſh with their concrete bodies. They are privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg'd with perpetuity a <hi>parte poſt</hi> as the Schools ſpeak. Tho' not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſimply, abſolutely, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialy, and independenly; yet <hi>per gratiam creationis,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99937:15"/> by ſingular favour beſtowed on them in their creation. Thoſe noble Eſſences, whatever darker minds may wildly imagin, were not deſign'd for a temporary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. Their nature is Immortal, and runs paralel with the longeſt line of endleſs duration. Their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin is derived from GOD himſelf, and when his All-powerful goodneſs formed them, he never meant that ſuch Glorious lights, ſhould only twinkle a little, and then go out: Glitter a while upon the ſtage of being, and ſo be thruſt down into the black abyſs of non-exiſtence.</p>
            <p>Indeed at Death he Suffers them to ſet in a Cloud, and lets them go down in the Horizon of time: But then it is that they may riſe in the Hemiſphaere of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and ſhine in the vertical of a future life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out declenſion. Death is ſo far from extinguiſhing the life of Souls, that it excites it, and makes it more energetical; raiſing them to an higher degree of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity, than any here poſſeſſed. It only cuts the cord of vital union, which ties them up in theſe rags of Fleſh, and ſtrips them of thoſe ſordid clothes of duſt, which dreſs them for Mortality. It only pricks the bladder of the Body, and refunds that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls the Soul) <hi>breath of the Immenſe mind, GOD,</hi> back unto Himſelf. O let us live like thoſe that have Souls, that have ſuch Immortal Souls to be ſowed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>What a vindication of Providence is here as to the Eternal perdition of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly?</hi> Diſmal things occur in Scripture, touching the final ſtate of Souls. We read there, that CHRIST's Church is <hi>a litle Flock:</hi> That the Gate of Life <hi>is ſtraight and narrow:</hi> And that there are <hi>few that ſhall be Saved.</hi> And many Father the event upon GOD, his Sovereign Power, and irreſpective Decree: And talk reflectingly againſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99937:16"/> his MAJESTY, as if he had arbitrarily condemned the greateſt part of Men, by irrevocable Sentence; to the moſt extreme and interminable Miſeries. But is this likely? Or can this be? When his own SON, his only Son, came into the World to ſave Sinners; all S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nners that will be ſaved?</p>
            <p>Much might be ſaid againſt this rigid, ſour, ill-natur'd Opinion, (which ſtrikes ſo directly at the GOODNESS of GOD, that central and radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perfection of his; and derogates from his kind and gracious Philanthropy with mighty diſparagement and defamation.) But it will not do well in confuting an Error to confront Authority. Yet this I will add, and I wiſh the whole World could hear it at once; and glad I am, that I ſpeak it this day in ſo celebrious an Aſſembly, becauſe it does right to the GOD of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is nothing leſs grateful, nothing more grievous to his Sacred MAIESTY, than the ruine of thoſe Souls which his hands have made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And O that none of Mankind might Periſh! But they that do ſo by abſolute Decree. Then all the Poſterity of fallen Adam, would be ſure to be Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Living GOD, and to triumph together in the Peace, and Joys, and Glories of his preſence, for evermore.</p>
            <p n="7">7. '<hi>Let no Perſons that repent truly of Sin, ever deſpair of their Salvation.</hi> I know it is the commune fault of Men, rather to preſume than deſpond of Happineſs. But tho' the many amongſt us be addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to preſumption; yet ſome may be in danger of the oppoſite Evil; and through the ſenſe and ſting of their own Guilt, and the curſed inſtigations of malicious Spirits, ſtrongly inclin'd to deſperation. And to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99937:16"/> ſuch the comfortable Doctrine of this Text, does next apply it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It bids them lift up their drooping Heads, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their kind and compaſſionate REDEEMER. It bids them look and ſee how he haſts and flies moſt ſwiftly towards them, with extended Arms of tender Mercy ready to embrace them. A ſight able to revive their gaſping hopes, and buoy up their heavy, penſive Hearts, though immers'd in greateſt depths of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. What! can we ſee the Son of GOD clothed with our Fleſh, and joined to our nature, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our own adoption a thing impoſſible? Can we ſee the high and mighty JESUS, come into the World to ſave Sinners; and yet think we cannot be ſaved by Him? They are ſunk into a low condition indeed, whom he cannot advance to Pardon and Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. He is able to ſave <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>to the uttermoſt.</hi> And no Sinners (relying on his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and Faithfully diſcharging their own duties) ever miſcarried or fell ſhort of Heaven, through deficiency in him, or any inability to conveigh them thither.</p>
            <p>'But we are apt to queſtion his <hi>will</hi> therefore, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than his <hi>Power,</hi> to ſave us. But I aſſure you we have little cauſe to do it. Does He not freely invite us to Salvation? <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden.</hi> Does he not promiſe to receive us if we come? <hi>Him that cometh unto me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Does he not complain, becauſe we will not come? <hi>Ye will not come to me that ye might have Life.</hi> Yea did he not grieve and weep to ſee Mens backwardneſs? So he did over the famous City: <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. And when CHRIST thus importunes us to come and be ſaved; promiſes to receive us, if we come; complains, and grieves, and weeps, becauſe we do not come: Can we think he is unwilling to ſave us?</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:99937:17"/>
            <p>Should we take our Bibles, and turn over the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of his bleſſed Incarnation, his holy Life, his bitter and his bloody paſſion; we could no where diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover or find out any thing, that looks like the leaſt unwillingneſs in CHRIST to ſave Sinners. If he were unwilling to do it, why did he come into the World on purpoſe? As the Text informs he did. Or when he had been a while here, and had felt in ſome meaſure, the weight and pungency of his direfull Sufferings; if he had not been willing to ſave Sinners, why did he not ſhrink and draw back, and refuſe to go through them, but meekly ſubmit to the tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them? We know what he once ſaid: He <hi>could have prayed his</hi> FATHER, <hi>and he would have ſent him more than twelve Legions of Angels.</hi> A ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Power to have reſcu'd him from a few ſilly and abuſive Worms. But he never put up this petition; and was he then unwilling to ſave us? O do not think ſo! Do not wrong him with ſuch a thought. Once indeed he prayed, that if it were poſſible, the <hi>Cup</hi> of his affliction might paſs from him. But therein he did not ſo much ſhow any reluctance or unwillingneſs to drink it off, as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding bitterneſs and acerbity of it. For at the ſame inſtant, he reſign'd himſelf wholly to GOD's diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and deſired to Die if he ſo pleaſed. <hi>Not my will, but thine be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if CHRIST be thus willing to ſave Sinners, then <hi>how comes it about, that the day of Grace ſhould ever be paſt with any in this Life?</hi> And that Men ſhould grow up to ſuch an height of Sin, as here to be debarr'd from the Mercy of Pardon, and even to anticipate their final Sentence, by being condemned before the Judgment?</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99937:17"/>
            <p>And To this I Anſwer, Firſt: <hi>it is a great Queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the day of Grace can be paſt ſo long as the day of Life continues.</hi> For the lewdeſt Perſons while they dwelt upon Earth, are no where ſaid to be fallen into ſo Ruful a Condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cain</hi> was a Man unmeaſurably Sinful: and ſo was <hi>Eſau:</hi> and ſo was <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> and ſo was <hi>Judas.</hi> Yet concerning the worſt of theſe, it was never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, that their Day of Grace was over in this World.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, <hi>Cain</hi> was thrown out of GODs preſence with a Curſe, But (ſo have many Excommunicated Perſons been) and if he had returned and ſought it by Obedience, he ſhould certainly have found Re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Favour.</p>
            <p>And of <hi>Eſau</hi> it is recorded, that he found no Place for Repentance, though he ſought it carefully with Tears. But then what Repentance was that which he ſought ſo mournfully? He did not ſeek to Repent of his Sins; but beſought his Father to Repent of his Bleſſing, that ſo he might have recovered the Right of Primogeniture, which he profanely alien'd to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This the ſight of his loſs, not the ſenſe of his Sins, made him weep and cry out with exceeding bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 27.) not to GOD, to have his Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes remitted; (then he had been happy;) but to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> to have his Bleſſing reverſed. But becauſe <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Benediction was irrevocable, therefore was <hi>Eſau</hi>'s La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation bootleſs.</p>
            <p>And touching <hi>Simon Magus</hi> we Read, that though he was <hi>in the gall of bitterneſs, and the bond of iniquity,</hi> ſoak'd in the virulence and venom of Sin, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect captive to the Devil; yet St. <hi>Peter</hi> adviſed him to Repent of his Wickedneſs, and to pray to GOD, <hi>if peradventure the thoughts of his Heart might be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99937:18"/> him.</hi> He was gone very far, when he was come to this. But though his Caſe was hazardous, it was not hopeleſs. For the Apoſtle would never have ſet him to work, if he had thought his Labour would have been in vain.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Judas,</hi> it is believed, that though his crime was of a monſtrous nature, and prodigiouſly aggravated by moſt horrid Circumſtances; yet Repentance would have brought him under the line of Mercy, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of Pardon. So St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> concludes in his Tractate <hi>de util. Paenit. Judam Traditorem, non tam ſcelus quod commiſit, quam indulgentiae deſperatio, fecit penitus interire. It was not ſo much the Villany he committed, as deſpair of Mercy, that made the Traytor</hi> Judas <hi>to Periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Day of Grace were not paſt with theſe ſo notorious Offenders, why ſhould it be paſt with any while alive.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the Quaere I Anſwer: <hi>If the day of Grace, may in this Life be paſt with us; this is conſiſtent enough with CHRIST's willingneſs to ſave us.</hi> For it is not long of him, but our ſelves, that the unhappineſs befalls us. While our <hi>LORD</hi> endeavours to reclaim us from our Sins, and Reduce us to himſelf: and we reſiſt the ſtrivings of his <hi>SPIRIT,</hi> and defeat the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his Providence, and elude the Methods of his Wiſdom, and fruſtrate the Contrivances of his Love and Kindneſs, deſtin'd to our good: we may hereby arrive at ſuch a pitch of Malice, as to be incapable of Salvation in ſome reſpect: at ſuch a pitch of Malice that the Ordinary influence and concurrence of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, which is ſufficient to other Mens Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will not be effective of ours. Nor is God obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged then to exert his Grace in <hi>mightier</hi> efforts and a Power <hi>irreſiſtible.</hi> No, rather (conſidering how we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99937:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> have deſpiſed his former Goodneſs) it is but juſt with him to withdraw the <hi>Commune</hi> Effluxes of it, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us (as he did that ſtubborn <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) to our ſelves. And then our Hearts, which would not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenerated and mollifi'd by his Grace, will grow more obſtinate and inflexible.</p>
            <p>When we are come into theſe Circumſtances, we may well ſuſpect that our Day of Grace is paſt indeed. For then we are unlike to get to Heaven, unleſs by <hi>extraordinary</hi> Diſpenſations, which GOD has promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to none, and very ſeldom affords to any. But then who is to blame for this? Not <hi>CHRIST,</hi> for he is willing to ſave us ſtill: but our ſelves alone, who have ſunk ſo deep into the Gulf of Sin, as to render our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergency into a State of Righteouſneſs extremely diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, and in the Courſe of GODs uſual dealings with Men, utterly impoſſible. And when by our vile &amp; licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious practices, we thus ſtraiten and block up our way to Heaven, and ſhut and bolt the Gate of Paradiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelves; we cannot complain that we are kept out, becauſe CHRIST is unwilling to let us in. No, amongſt all the outcries of Periſhing Souls, that pierce the horrible Regions of Darkneſs, and eccho in the diſmal Caverns of Hell, I dare boldly ſay, there is none like this: <hi>That they Languiſh and die in endleſs miſery, for CHRIST</hi>'s <hi>being loth to ſave them from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then (may ſome diſſolute <hi>Miſcreants</hi> ſay) if the Caſe ſtands thus: if none may deſpair, if all may be ſaved; then what good news is here for us? we may then continue where we are, and lay down and reſt in our old delights, and go on with confidence in our Sinful Pleaſure, and yet do well enough at laſt.</p>
            <p>But to them that talk at this extravagant rate, I reply in ſhort; My deſign was not to encourage the ſinful, but to ſupport the ſorrowful. Not to harden
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99937:19"/> the preſumptuous, but to relieve the penitent. To build a Sanctuary for the contrite, not a refuge for the careleſs. And if they will ſnatch the Doctrine out of my mouth, and make it miniſter to evil pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; be it known unto them, they do great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice to their own Intereſts. If like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, they will turn a ſtaff into a ſerpent; or change an antidote to deadly poyſon: if they'l burn by that fire, which was kindled to warm them; and ſurfeit of that food which was prepar'd to nouriſh them; who can help it? Themſelves muſt anſwer for their wilfull ruine; and by inverting the uſe of ſuch whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome remedies, ſhall periſh like fools, and none ſhall pity them.</p>
            <p>For albeit CHRIST is willing to ſave us, yet ſave us he will, on his <hi>own</hi> terms, and in his <hi>own</hi> way. And how is that? The Scripture certifies.</p>
            <p>GOD <hi>ſent his</hi> SON <hi>to bleſs us, in turning every one of us from our Iniquities.</hi> And CHRIST <hi>gave himſelf for us, that he might REDEEM us from all Iniquity.</hi> So that firſt he ſaves us from ſin, and then from miſery. That's the progreſſive method or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which he has fixt and preſcribed to himſelf, in carrying on and compleating the work of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Firſt he reſcues us from the reign, and power, and practice of Sin: and then from the guilt, and curſe, and puniſhment of it. If therefore we mean to perſiſt in Sin, it behoves us to ſeek out for <hi>another</hi> SAVIOUR, if in the end we would be happy. And we cannot but remember, that this Inference, counſels none againſt deſpairing of Salvation, <hi>but ſuch as repent, and repent truly of Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>How little cauſe have we to diſtruſt Providence, as to our temporal maintenance!</hi> GOD that honoured us with ſo great a bleſſing as JESUS's Advent, will
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99937:19"/> not deny us thoſe that are leſs. 'Tis the Apoſtles In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from the ſame Doctrine. <hi>He that ſpared not his SON, but delivered him up for us all; How ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things?</hi> He that paid ſuch a vaſt price for our Souls, will not neglect them while they dwell in theſe Bodies. He will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly vouchſafe us as much as we <hi>need;</hi> though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not ſo much as we <hi>wiſh.</hi> What the Pſalmiſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, we may boldly believe; <hi>they that fear the LORD, ſhall lack no manner of thing that is good.</hi> They may lack many things good in themſelves, but nothing that is good for them. He that fed <hi>Elijah</hi> by the miniſtry of Ravens, and the <hi>Sereptan</hi> Widdow by miraculous augmentation of her exhauſted proviſions; will find out ways for our competent ſubſiſtence, in our greateſt deſtitution of neceſſary ſupplies: and will take care that we ſhall never want, what it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for us to enjoy.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Since CHRIST JESUS came into the World to ſave ſinners, <hi>how ſhould we laud him for that ſignal Mercy?</hi> It is the higheſt and moſt glorious favour, that ever we received at his hands: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for it, we ſhould exceed in gratitude. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Church in a deep ſenſe of this incumbent Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, has appointed the <hi>Benedictus,</hi> that moſt admirable Hymn or Song of Bleſſing for our SAVIOUR's Incarnation, to be offered up to GOD in her Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Devotions: and mentions it alſo in the General Thankſgiving; and good reaſon. For had he given us leave to ask what we would; and a promiſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whatever we asked; we could not have requeſted any thing ſo great: yet this he imparted, undeſired. Yea, if GOD had ſtudied and caſt about with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to all Eternity, he could not have invented or projected for us, a more noble kindneſs. O that Men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99937:20"/> would therefore praiſe the LORD, for this his GOODNESS. But Men alone cannot do it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: let the whole Creation make one Quire, and joyn in conſort to celebrate his Name with ſolemn Praiſes. Let the Saints and Angels praiſe him. Let the Heavens and the Earth praiſe him. Let the World, let both the Worlds, and all that is therein praiſe him. But above all, let every ſincere Penitent rouze up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as the good Man did; Praiſe thou the LORD, O my Soul. Methinks we ſhould wiſh we had a Thouſand Tongues to ſing forth thankful Anthems to his MAJESTY: And that our ſelves were turned all into Harmony, that ſo we might extol him with the ſweeteſt Melody. But being ſure we are unable to praiſe him ſufficiently here upon Earth, let us reſolve to do what we can, and let the reſt alone till we get to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Where our faint, and flat, and low magnificats, ſhall riſe up to Divine and lofty Hallelujahs, and run out in moſt high and Eternal Doxologies.</p>
            <p>I now conclude with this one Corollary. <hi>Such is the ſweetneſs, ſuch the uſefulneſs of the Text before us, that it ought never to be forgotten by us.</hi> Let us ſet it therefore continually in our ſight. Let us fix it in our minds, and Print it in our memories, and every day revolve it in our cogitations. It is as choice, as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick a place, as any in the Bible. CHRIST JESUS <hi>came into the World to ſave ſinners:</hi> what a ſtrange gratification drops and diſtills, from the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting words? They are more fragrant than Perfumes; more ſavory than Banquets: more precious than Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; more powerful than Rhetorick: more cordial than Wine; more healing than Balm: more taking than Beauty; more raviſhing than Love. I know not what to ſay, to expreſs my own Sentiments of them; much leſs to ſet forth their native Excellence. They are more valuable than all the World, to repenting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99937:20"/> Sinners. And all the felicities in the World, cannot lift them up to ſuch a degree of rapturous Joy, as that which ſpreads and flows through their Souls, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſerious contemplation of this moſt <hi>faithful, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſaying,</hi> CHRIST JESUS <hi>came into the World to ſave Sinners.</hi> To whom be all Glory, Love, and Obedience, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
